John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Corporate Structure, RG 1 FA1793
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Corporate Structure, RG 1
1950-2019
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation
FA1793
34.56 Cubic Feet (94 containers)
Scope and Contents
Record Group 1, Corporate Structure, contains the Foundation's incorporation papers and files relating to the Board of Trustees. These include packets of grant-related materials for each board meeting, committee files, correspondence, manuals, and organizational charts. The meeting minutes are particularly significant to this Subgroup because they detail all the actions and decisions made by the Board of Trustees since the Foundation's inception in 1950, and the Board Books provide insight into the grant-making process after 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as follows:
Subgroup 1: Board of Trustees
Series 1: Activity Reports
Series 2: Biographical Files (See Record Group 4 for Trustee Biographical Files)
Series 3: Committees
Series 4: Correspondence
Series 5: Manuals
Series 6: Meetings
Subgroup 2: Incorporation Papers
Series 1: Amendments
Series 2: Articles of Incorporation
Series 3: By-Laws
Subgroup 3: Organizational Charts
- Board of Trustees, 1950-2019; 1; 33.99 Cubic Feet 87 letter document boxes and 5 half-letter boxes
  - Activity Reports, 1989-2005; 1; 3.04 Cubic Feet 8 letter document boxes
    Scope and Contents
    The activity reports, also known as trustee packets, are prepared by the Communications Department for the trustees as informative reading before board meetings. They are a compilation of newspaper and magazine articles about Knight Foundation staff, trustees and programs as well as correspondence, including letters and notes from grantees.
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1-13)
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 1-10)
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1995-1997 May (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1997 August (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1997 November (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1998 June (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Includes coverage of programs (Knight Center for Specialized Journalism, youth violence, etc.), Larry Meyer's article re. community foundations and newspapers relationships, Knight Ridder's relocation from Miami, etc.
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1998 December (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Includes coverage of programs [Education (Communities in Schools, etc.), Community Initiatives (National Center for Family Literacy, Youth Violence), Arts & Culture (Magic of Music, Museum Loan Network, etc.), Journalism (Knight Chairs, international journalism programs), the activities of Hodding Carter, an editorial by Ben Maidenberg, Center for Specialized Journalism, youth violence, etc.), and Larry Meyer on the importance of philanthropy.
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1999 June (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Includes coverage of the Foundation's new IDEAS fund (NewTown Macon), programs [Education (Read, Write and Type!, etc.), Community Initiatives (National Center for Family Literacy, Youth Violence), Arts & Culture (Magic of Music, Museum Loan Network, etc.), Journalism ("American Journalism Review" AJR), the election of Ben Maidenberg to the Board of Trustees, and interviews with Hodding Carter.
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 1999 October (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Includes coverage of programs and grantees [Education (Teach for America, Institute for School Innovation), Community Initiatives (National Center for Family Literacy, Youth Violence, NewTown Macon), Arts and Culture (Magic of Music, Ohr-O'Keefe Museum,, etc.), Journalism (Inter-American Press Assoc. funding for rapid response team in response to violence against journalists in Latin America). Also clippings re. Penny McPhee, Linda Raybin, opening of James L. Knight International Center.
    - News Coverage and Correspondence, 2000 February (Box 6, Folder 7)
      Includes coverage of programs and grantees, the death of Lee Hills (2/3/2000), Knight Center in Akron, Drake Conference, etc.
    - News Coverage, 2000 November (Box 6, Folder 8)
      Includes coverage of programs and grantees, Knight Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics, etc.
    - News Coverage, 2001 August-2003 March (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
    - News Coverage, 2003 July (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Includes coverage of programs and grantees, Knight Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics, National Venture Fund, Community Partners, Journalism Initiatives and trustees and staff.
    - News Coverage, 2004 January (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - News Coverage, 2004 June (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - News Coverage, 2004 November (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Includes coverage of programs and grantees, community foundations, launch of the immigration initiative, and Knight Commission on Intercollegiate Athletics. Also included are profiles on trustee Cesar Alvarez and a transcript of Hodding Carter's Ralph McGill lecture.
    - News Coverage, 2005 May (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Includes a memo from Larry Meyer re: a sample electronic summary of recent coverage available online. Printed newsclips are being phased out. This packet includes a list of online articles and reprints re: donor-advised funds, community foundations and recent grants.
  - Committees, 1950-2019; 3; 18.42 Cubic Feet 47 letter document boxes and 3 half-letter boxes
    - List of Committee Appointments, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      1995 appointees to Nominating, Distribution, Finance and Planning Committees.
    - List of Committee Appointments, 1991-1996 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      Committee membership lists, 1991-1996 for Nominating, Finance, Distribution, Planning and Program Committees.
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Conflict of Interest, 1999; 1
      - Minutes of the Ad Hoc Committee on Conflict of Interest, 1999 January 10 (Box 9, Folder 3)
        Recommendations on potential trustee and staff conflicts in dealing with self-dealing, gifts and honoraria, and grants.
    - Administrative and Human Resources/Human Resources and Administrative, 1997-2006; 2
      The name of the committee was changed to "Administrative and Human Resources" in 1998. Staffing, benefits, organizational structure, and policies and procedures are some of the concerns addressed by this committee.
      - Meeting Materials, 1997 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Meeting materials for the Human Resources and Administrative Committee Meeting (also includes materials for the Finance Committee Meeting), held on 12/8/97 in Miami, FL. Materials include the minutes of the Human Resources and Administrative Committee meeting of 9/15/97, Admin./HR activities update and agenda for 1998, 1997/1998 Administrative Expense Budgets, 403 (b) Distribution Discussion, 1997/1998 Program Initiatives. Also included are the materials for the Finance Committee of 12/8/97.
      - Human Resources & Administrative Committee, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Agenda and minutes of the quarterly meeting of the Human Resources and Administrative Committee. Includes updates re. benefits, recruitment, Archives and document management, and the John S. Knight Papers at the University of Akron. Also contains a Board of Trustees resolution concerning the Archives and Document Management Policy.
      - Meeting Materials, 1998 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Agenda and minutes of the quarterly meeting (3/16/1998) of the Human Resources and Administrative Committee. Includes updates re. benefits; recruitment; the Knight Foundation Internship Program; an issue of Knight News, the employee newsletter; Leadership Miami; and Archives and document management. Also contains a Board of Trustees resolution concerning the Archives and Document Management Policy.
      - Meeting Materials, 1998 September 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Meeting materials for the Human Resources and Administrative Committee Meeting, held on 9/14/98 in Miami, FL. Materials include the minutes of the Human Resources and Administrative Committee meeting of 6/14/98, a staffing report, an update on organization staffing, job analysis, compensation, performance management, and salary administration, and an update on total compensation and benefits.
      - Meeting Materials, 1998 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Meeting Materials, 1999 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Agenda and discussion items for the Administrative and Human resources committee meeting, which also included the pension plans administrative and investment committees. Also included is a Finance Department Organization Study and presentation materials concerning retirement benefit design issues.
      - Agenda and Meeting Materials, 1999 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Agenda and discussion items for the Administrative and Human resources committee meeting. Discussion items include the Foundation's retirement plan.
      - Agenda and Meeting Materials, 1999 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Agenda and discussion items for the Administrative and Human resources committee meeting. Discussion items include the Foundation's retirement plan, investment staff, and flexible benefits plan.
      - Agenda and Meeting Materials, 1999 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Agenda and discussion items for the Administrative and Human resources committee meeting. Discussion items include the Foundation's staffing plan, retirement plan, and budget review..
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2000 March 13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Agenda and materials for the quarterly meeting of the Administrative and Human Resources Committee. Includes updates re. benefit plan renewals, pension benefits documents, Third Amendment to the KF Section 403(b) Plan Resolution and Certification and recruitment. Also includes minutes of the December 6, 1999 meeting.
      - Knight Foundation Staff Plan, 2000 May 25 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Staff Plan consists of a report with sections on the Knight Foundation's Organization Staffing Study, Strategic Planning Recommendations, Work Resource Alternatives, Cost Breakdown for Additional Staff, Proposed Organization Chart, Memo to Board of Trustees, and the Hamilton Report from 1996. Also included is a summary memo written by Belinda Lawrence and approved by Hodding Carter.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2000 June 12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Agenda and materials for the quarterly meeting of the Administrative and Human Resources Committee. Includes updates re. staffing and recruiting, retirement plan, staff compensation, and flexible benefits. Also included are minutes of the March 2000 Administrative and Human Resources Committee and Pension Plan committees meetings.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2000 September 10 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Agenda and materials for the quarterly meeting of the Administrative and Human Resources Committee. Includes updates re: staffing and recruitment, compensation, benefits and the 403(b) plan. Also includes minutes of the June 12, 2000 meeting.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2000 December 4 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Includes updates re. staffing and recruiting, retirement plan, staff activities, and flexible benefits. Also included are minutes of the September 2000 Administrative and Human Resources Committee and Pension Plan meeting and a review of the 2000 and 2001 budgets.
      - Meeting Minutes, 2001 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting update, administrative and Human Resources activities, resolution on succession of the President by the Vice President, Health Care and Vision service insurance renewal, lease in One Biscayne Tower, Tax Gross-Up rates, summary analysis of the 2000 budget, Human Resources strategies, and Knowledge Management.
      - Pension Plan Administrative Committee and Pension Plan Investment Committee Meeting, 2001 March 12 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        Agenda items for discussion include a summary of investment returns, review of Vanguard Group funds, pension administrative report, retirement (403b) plan, By-Laws, strategic plan, cost and financial information, 401k plan proposal, and Safe Harbor Match to a 401k plan. Also included are the March 2000 pension plan committee minutes.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Meeting, 2001 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting update, administrative and Human Resources activities, pension reform provisions, administrative budget analysis, and program initiatives 2001 final budget. Also included are minutes of the March 2001 meetings of the Admin. and HR and Pension Plan committees.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Meeting, 2001 September 10 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting update, administrative and Human Resources activities, health insurance for out-of-state employees, 403(b) plan, and accounting for program initiatives. Also included are minutes of the June 2001 meeting of the Admin. and HR committee.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Meeting, 2001 December 3 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting update, administrative and Human Resources activities, personnel policy update, and budget review. Also included are minutes of the September 2001 meeting of the Admin. and HR committee.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2002 March 11 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting, administrative and human resources activities, health insurance, leasing options, and a summary analysis of 2001 general and administrative expenses. Also included are minutes of the December 4, 2001 meeting.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2002 June 9 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting, administrative and human resources activities, and the 401(h) account for retirement plan. Also included are minutes of the March meetings of the Administrative and Human Resources and Pension Plan committees.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2002 September 9 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting, administrative and human resources activities, a benefits management report, and a First Union building status report. Also included are minutes of the June 2002 meeting.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2002 December 9 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2003 March 10 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting, administrative and human resources activities, the retirement plan, the move to the First Union building, and the 2003 budget. Also included are minutes of the December 2002 meeting of the Administrative and Human Resources committee.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2003 June 9 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting, administrative and human resources activities, the retirement plan, the move to the First Union building, and an updated organization chart. Also included are minutes of the March 2003 quarterly meeting of the Administrative and Human Resources committee and the minutes of the annual meeting of the pension plan administrative committee and the pension plan investment committee from March 2003. Minutes of the meeting are also included.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2003 September 8 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting, administrative and human resources activities, the retirement plan, the move to the Wachovia Financial Center, a benefits management report and an updated organization chart.. Also included are minutes of the June 2003 quarterly meeting of the Administrative and Human Resources committee.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2003 December 8 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting, administrative and human resources activities, the retirement plan, the 2004 budget and an updated organization chart. Also included are minutes of the September 2003 quarterly meeting of the Administrative and Human Resources committee.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2004 June 14 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        Includes discussion of staffing and recruiting, administrative and human resources activities, the retirement plan, an updated organization chart and a memo re: art purchases for the Wachovia offices. Also included are minutes of the March 2004 quarterly meeting of the Administrative and Human Resources committee and the annual meetings of the pension plan administrative committee and the pension plan investment committee.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2004 September 13 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        Meeting took place on September 12, via teleconference, due to hurricane threat. Includes minutes of June 14, 2004 meeting; staffing update; legal and regulatory compliance update; business insurance summary; and a benefit plan update.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2004 December 6 (Box 4, Folder 4)
        Includes minutes of September 12, 2004 meeting; organization chart; staffing update; a benefit plan update; and a 2005 budget report. Also included are minutes of the December 6 meeting.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2005 June 6 (Box 4, Folder 7)
        Includes minutes of March 2005 meetings of the administrative and pension plan committees; organization chart; staffing update; a benefit plan update; and a report on KF workforce stability. Also included is a resolution, dated June 6, 2005 re: amendment to the Retirement Plan for Foundation employees.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2005 September 19 (Box 4, Folder 8)
        Includes minutes of June 2005 meetings of the administrative committees; organization chart; staffing update; a Risk Assessment Review; and a discussion of sub-leasing part of the Knight Foundation's offices.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee Meeting, 2005 December 12 (Box 4, Folder 9)
        Includes minutes of September and December 2005 meetings of the administrative committees; organization chart; staffing update; a discussion of the KF retirement trust; and the 2006 budget report.
      - Administrative and Human Resources Committee, 2006 June 12 (Box 4, Folder 10)
        Materials for the Administrative and Human Resources Committee include minutes of the March 13, 2006 meeting and the pension plan meetings on the same date, and a staffing update with organization chart.
    - Audit Committee, 2001-2019; 3
      Regular agenda items include discussions with the Knight Foundation independent auditors and the financial statement.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2001 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Agenda items include discussions with the Knight Foundation's independent auditors and concerning the financial statement.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2001 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Agenda items include a review of the financial statement, clarification of the Audit Committee roles and responsibilities, and audit planning. Also included are minutes of the meeting.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2002 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Agenda items include approval of March 11, 2002 minutes, discussion of Tim Crowe and Betty Clossick re: investment risks and controls and the financial statement.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2002 September 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Agenda items include approval of June 9, 2002 minutes; information on financial reporting oversight and the Sarbanes-Oxley Act of 2002; and financial statements. Included is a publication from Ernst and Young re: Audit Committees: Providing Oversight in Challenging Times.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2002 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Agenda items include discussions with the Knight Foundation's independent auditors (Ernst and Young) and the financial statement.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2003 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Agenda items include approval of December 9, 2002 minutes; and discussion on the report of the independent auditors and the audit results. Included is a general and administrative expense summary and analysis.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2003 June 9 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Agenda items include minutes of the March 10, 2003 minutes; current items of interest; financial statements and narrative for the first quarter 2003; and administrative expense summary and analysis for the first quarter 2003.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2003 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Agenda items include approval of June 9, 2003 minutes; and discussions on diversity at Ernst and Young, a grantee audit study, hedge fund best practices and staff credit card limits. Included is a general and administrative expense summary and analysis.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2003 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Agenda items include approval of September 8, 2003 minutes; and discussions on hedge fund due diligence, internal auditing practices at other foundations, and Ernst and Young fees. Included is a general and administrative expense summary and analysis.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2004 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Included are minutes of the December 8, 2003 meeting; a report of the independent auditors and audited financial statements; audit results; current items of interest; and general and administrative expense summary and analysis.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2004 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Included are minutes of the March 8, 2004 meeting; a memo regarding the presentation of non-profits vs. for-profit financial reporting and its impact on the Knight Foundation; a memo regarding the presentation of internal controls surrounding cash transfers; current items of interest; check/wire transfer authority and investment authority; audit committee charter; financial statements and narratives; and administrative expense summary and analysis.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2004 September 12 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Committee meeting was held one day ahead of schedule and via conference call due to a hurricane threat. Included with minutes are an insurance coverage summary update; and a draft of an updated audit committee charter and board resolution.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2004 December 6 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        Included are minutes of the September 12, 2004 meeting; an audit plan; 2004 Ernst and Young fees; current items of interest; financial statements and narratives; and administrative expense summary and analysis.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2005 March 14 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Included are minutes of the December 6, 2004 meeting; a report of the independent auditors and audited financial statements; audit results; check/wire transfer authority and investment authority; general and administrative expense summary and analysis; and current items of interest.
      - Audit Committee Meeting, 2005 June 6 (Box 2, Folder 4)